Finding Aid for Bradley v. Milliken case files, 1962-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bradley v. Milliken case files 1962-1976, 1970-1974
Roth, Stephen J.
12 linear feet
2009170 Aa 2
The Honorable Stephen J. Roth presided over the landmark school desegregation case Bradley v. Milliken in the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, Southern Division from 1970 until his death in 1974. Roth ruled that the Detroit Public School system was guilty of de jure segregation and ordered the implementation of an inter-district metropolitan busing plan to achieve integration. The case eventually reached the U.S. Supreme Court, which declared Roth’s remedy to be impermissible and emphasized local control of schools in its July 1974 decision (Milliken v. Bradley 418 U.S. 717). The case files include trial materials (pleadings, desegregation plans, court transcripts, etc.), appellate materials, opinions and orders, correspondence, and clippings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The case files were donated by John R. and Ann M. Runyan (donor no. 10277 ) in October 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Stephen J. Roth was born in Hungary on April 21, 1908 and immigrated to the United States at an early age. He was raised in Flint, Michigan, attended Notre Dame University, and received his law degree at the University of Michigan. His first foray into the public sphere occurred when, having served as a prosecutor in Genesee County, he was elected state Attorney General in 1948. Defeated in 1950, Roth was named a Genesee County judge in 1952 and remained in this position until President Kennedy nominated him for a seat on the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan in 1962.
Bradley v. Milliken had its roots in an integration plan put forth by the Detroit Board of Education on April 7, 1970. The 'April 7th Plan', as it was known, called for the reassignment of 9,000 high school students to achieve a measure of desegregation and drew immediate protest from white enclaves in Detroit and led to the formation of Concerned Citizens for Better Education (CCBE). Composed mainly of white parents' and homeowners' groups, CCBE organized a petition drive to recall the liberal Board of Education members responsible for the April 7 plan. The public outcry also led the Michigan State Legislature to nullify the April 7 plan by enacting Public Act 48, section 12 of which stated, "the implementation of any attendance provisions for the 1970-71 school year determined by any first class school board shall be delayed."
In an effort to overturn section 12, a group of mostly black families including Ronald and Richard Bradley and their mother, Vera, joined with the NAACP to challenge its constitutionality. Their suit was initially brought forth in the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan on August 18, 1970. Defendants initially included Governor William G. Milliken, Attorney General Frank Kelley, the Michigan State Board of Education, State Superintendent of Public Instruction John W. Porter, the Detroit Board of Education and the Superintendent of Detroit Public Schools but subsequently included a number of intervening defendants. After Judge Roth refused to grant a preliminary injunction, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit found section 12 to be unconstitutional but at the same time declined to rule on the school board's obligations or the merits of any desegregation plan. Although the plaintiffs sought to force the implementation of the April 7 plan, Roth instead required the Detroit Board of Education to develop a plan that would parallel the previous integration levels. On December 3, 1970, Judge Roth selected the 'McDonald' (or Magnet) Plan from three submissions and ordered its implementation by the next full school year.
The plaintiffs once more appealed to the Circuit Court, which in turn directed that a trial in the District Court proceed on the merits. This trial ran from April 5, 1971 to July 22, 1971 and concluded in Judge Roth's decision on September 27, 1971 that the defendants were liable for de jure segregation (that is, segregation enforced by law). Roth's finding in the matter noted that "Governmental actions and inaction at all levels, federal, state, and local, have combined with those of private organizations [...] to establish and maintain the pattern of residential segregation throughout the Detroit Metropolitan area."
The next stage of the Bradley v. Milliken involved the remedy with which to correct the segregation endemic to the Detroit Public School system. Hearings were held intermittently from October 4, 1971 through March 21, 1972 on Detroit-only desegregation plans. These proceedings sought to determine if an effective--and constitutionally sound--desegregation plan could be promulgated within Detroit alone or if the entire metropolitan area would have to be involved. On March 24, Roth produced a "Ruling on the Propriety of Considering a Metropolitan Remedy to Accomplish Desegregation" and this led to hearings on inter-district plans from March 28 through April 14, 1972. Various plans were produced by plaintiffs, the State Board of Education, the Detroit Board of Education, and intervening defendants, Denise Magdowski, et al. The culmination of these hearings was Roth's June 14, 1972 "Ruling on Desegregation Area and Order for Development of Plan of Desegregation" which established a nine person (soon to be eleven) panel to produce a plan for integration in Detroit and 53 surrounding school districts.
Following Roth's ruling, State defendants sought a stay or suspension of proceedings; denied by Roth, they eventually asked the Supreme Court to review the entire case theretofore. In the meantime, Roth moved forward with the transportation logistics necessary to implement a desegregation plan and to that end found that the Detroit Board of Education was required to purchase an additional 295 school buses. From July 1972 through June 1973, the Sixth Circuit heard various appeals of Roth's rulings; an en banc rehearing initiated in January 1973 vacated portions of Roth's Ruling on Desegregation Area but ultimately supported his metropolitan remedy.
The Supreme Court granted defendants' petitions for a writ of certiorari on November 19, 1973 and hearings began on February 27, 1974. The sharply divided Court rejected Roth's solution in its opinion on July 25, 1974, ruling that:
Before the boundaries of separate and autonomous school districts may be set aside by consolidating the separate units for remedial purposes or by imposing a cross-district remedy, it must first be shown that there has been a constitutional violation within one district that produces significant segregative effect in another district.
By virtue of its emphasis on local control in schools, the Court's decision in Bradley v. Milliken (418 U.S. 717) effectively exempted suburbs from aiding in the desegregation of inner-city schools and gave further impetus to 'white flight' from cities.
Two weeks before the Court's ruling, Stephen J. Roth suffered his third heart attack in three years and died on July 11, 1974. His four years at the helm of Bradley v. Milliken saw him praised by civil rights activists and honored by the ACLU and excoriated in newspapers and bumper stickers ("Roth is a four letter word" being a particularly popular one). Noted as a conservative among his friends, Roth was initially skeptical of the involvement of 'outsiders' in the affairs of the Detroit Public Schools. Nonetheless, the evidence and testimony of Detroit's segregation made a profound impression and led him to take a principled--and highly unpopular--stand for equality and fairness in education. Bradley v. Milliken continued after Roth's demise and it was not until 1989 that it was adjudged "that the Detroit school system is a 'unitary' school system and has eliminated all vestiges of past de jure segregation."
The Stephen J. Roth Bradley v. Milliken case files provide original source materials from one of the most contentious and influential desegregation cases in our nation's history. In addition to transcripts, court documents, and rulings, the collection permits scholar and citizen alike the opportunity to better understand Roth's conclusions and rulings with its rich trove of annotated briefs, personal law notes, manuscript drafts of opinions, and personal correspondence. Numerous secondary sources, including news clippings, appellate and Supreme Court decisions, and reports and journals consulted by Roth offer a rich context in which to understand the significance of the case in the history of Michigan and the nation as a whole. The Bradley v. Milliken case files consist of one series divided into seven subseries; the present arrangement reflects the order in which the materials were received from John Runyan, a former law clerk of Judge Roth's. Relevant materials have been added to case files over the years and this accumulation accounts for materials extant from 1975-1976.
Subjects:
Bradley, Richard.; Bradley, Ronald.; Busing for school integration--Michigan--Detroit.; Discrimination in education--Law and legislation--United States.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Roth, Stephen J.; United States. District Court (Michigan: Eastern District); Bradley, Richard.; Bradley, Ronald.; Milliken, William G., 1922-
- Bradley v. Milliken case files
  The Bradley v. Milliken case files consist of one series divided into 7 subseries; the present arrangement reflects the order in which the materials were received from John Runyan, a former law clerk of Judge Roth's. Relevant materials have been added to case files over the years and this accumulation accounts for materials extant from 1975-1976.
  - Trial materials
    The Trial Materials subseries is the most extensive in the collection and consists of items from various phases of the legal proceedings. These include trial briefs from the initial injunction de jure segregation, and remedy hearings; desegregation plans and responses; intervention documents and materials related to transportation logistics; pleadings; exhibits; and transcripts of court proceedings from August 1970 through July 1972.
    - Trial briefs
      - Complaint August 1970 (Box 1)
        ("a suit for declaratory judgment declaring certain portions of Act No. 48 of the Michigan Public Acts of 1970 [...] unconstitutional.")
        (1-1)
      - [Plaintiffs'] Memorandum brief and memorandum of points and authorities August 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-2)
      - Memorandum brief of defendant Board of Education of the city of Detroit August 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-3)
      - Brief of Michigan State Board of Education, a constitutional body corporate, and John W. Porter, acting Superintendent of Public Instruction, defendants August 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-4)
      - Motion to dismiss on behalf of William J. Milliken, Governor of the state of Michigan and ex-officio member of Michigan State Board of Education, and Frank J. Kelley, Attorney General of the state of Michigan August 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-5)
      - Answer to complaint on behalf of defendants the Board of Education of the city of Detroit; Patrick A. McDonald; James A. Hathaway; Cornelius L. Golightly and Norman Drachler August 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-6)
      - [Plaintiffs'] Pre trial brief ("The Constitutional Mandate for Non-Segregated Public Education"); Motion to implement April 7th plan October 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-7)
      - Trial brief on behalf of defendants the Board of Education of the city of Detroit; Patrick A. McDonald; James A. Hathaway; Cornelius L. Golightly and Norman Drachler October 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-8)
      - State defendants' trial brief October 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-9)
      - Class action documents November 1970-February 1971 (regarding the class standing of plaintiffs; includes memoranda by state defendants and the Detroit Board of Education) (Box 1)
        (1-10)
      - [Detroit Board of Education's] Motion for continuance November 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-11)
      - [Detroit Board of Education's] Reply to plaintiff's motion to implement plan including discussion of authorities November 1970 (Box 1)
        (1-12)
      - State defendants' brief in support of motion to quash or modify subpoenas duces tecum April 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-13)
      - Motion to dismiss on behalf of William J. Milliken, Governor of the state of Michigan and ex-officio member of Michigan State Board of Education, and Frank J. Kelley, Attorney General of the state of Michigan May 1971 (Box 1)
        (includes a brief in support of and memorandum in opposition to the state defendants' motion to dismiss)
        (1-14)
      - Proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law submitted on behalf of the state defendants May 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-15)
      - [Plaintiffs'] Conclusions of law July 1971 (Box 1)
        (original copy)
        (1-16)
      - [Plaintiffs'] Conclusions of law July 1971 (Box 1)
        (corrected copy)
        (1-17)
      - Supplemental proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law submitted on behalf of the state defendants; Supplemental brief in support of state defendants' motions to dismiss July 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-18)
      - Proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law, by Detroit Federation of Teachers, intervening defendant and Brief of intervening Defendant Detroit Federation of Teachers July 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-19)
      - [Detroit Board of Education's] Proposed conclusions of law July 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-20)
      - Memorandum brief of state defendants July 1971 (Box 1)
        (1-21)
      - Brief of defendant Detroit Board of Education August 1971 (Box 1)
        (includes table of contents and index to authorities)
        (1-22)
      - Plaintiffs' proposed findings, conclusions, and order on Detroit-only desegregation plans March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-23)
      - Brief of defendant School Board for the school district of the city of Detroit and other defendants in support of metropolitan plan based on testimony elicited at hearing on Detroit-only plan March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-24)
      - Brief of state defendants on the legal propriety or impropriety of consideration by this court of a metropolitan plan March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-25)
      - Brief on law in support of metropolitan plan presented by defendant School Board for the city of Detroit and other defendants March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-26)
      - Intervening defendant Denise Magdowski's brief on the metropolitan remedy March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-27)
      - Plaintiffs' memorandum of law on metropolitan school desegregation March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-28)
      - Brief of defendants-intervenor Tri-County Citizens et al. on propriety of metropolitan remedy March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-29)
      - Brief of defendant-intervenor Grosse Pointe Public School System re metropolitan plans of desegregation March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-30)
      - Brief of Southfield Public Schools March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-31)
      - Brief of defendants-intervenors Allen Park Public Schools, et al. re: legal impropriety of a so-called metropolitan plan of desegregation March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-32)
      - Defendant Detroit Board of Education and other defendants proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law following hearings on Detroit-only remedy March 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-33)
      - Defendant Detroit Board of Education and other defendants proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law following hearings on metropolitan Detroit desegregation plans; Brief of defendant Detroit Board of Education and other defendants in support of proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law and the board's metropolitan Detroit plan May 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-34)
      - [Grosse Pointe Schools'] Memorandum in opposition to adoption of metropolitan plan of desegregation May 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-35)
      - Announcement on the distribution of copies of the Court's "ruling on desegregation area and order for development of plan of desegregation" and "findings of fact and conclusions of law" June 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-36)
      - [Plaintiffs'] Memorandum in opposition to stay applications July 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-37)
      - Motion of defendant Detroit Board of Education for partial entry of judgment 1972 (Box 1)
        (1-38)
    - Desegregation plans and responses
      - Relevant rulings and orders
        - Memorandum opinion and order 1971 (Box 1)
          (1-39)
        - Order for preparing metropolitan desegregation plans 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-40)
        - Ruling on desegregation area and development of plan 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-41)
      - Plaintiffs (NAACP et al.)
        - Desegregation Plan: Detroit Public Schools February 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-42)
        - Plaintiffs' motion for an order adjudging defendant Detroit's plans to be legally insufficient and for other relief; Plaintiffs' memorandum in support of motion March 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-43)
        - [Plaintiffs'] Request for leave to file supplemental, particularized objection to [Desegregation] Panel's report, minority report, and state superintendent's reports August 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-44)
      - Detroit Board of Education
        - School Integration Plan April 1970 (Box 1)
          (1-45)
        - The Magnet School Program: A Progress Report November 1971 (Box 1)
          (1-46)
        - Compliance with court order of 11/05/1971, December 1971 (Box 1)
          (includes Board of Education resolutions, two desegregation plans, and an accompanying memorandum brief)
          (1-47)
        - Objections of Board of Education for the city of Detroit and other defendants to the metropolitan plan submitted by the state of Michigan and by way of an alternative, a submission herein by said board of a metropolitan Detroit area integration plan March 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-48)
        - Plans for implementation of integration plan A March 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-49)
        - Objections of Board of Education for the city of Detroit and other defendants to the alleged plan of desegregation filed by plaintiffs March 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-50)
        - Defendant Board of Education for the city of Detroit answer to plaintiffs' motion for order adjudging defendant's Detroit plans to be legally insufficient March 1972 (Box 1)
          (1-51)
        - Defendants-Intevenor Denise Magdowski et al.: "The Designation and Integration of Public Schools in Detroit" January 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-1)
        - Objection of Detroit Federation of Teachers to proposed Detroit plan of plaintiffs, and to proposed "Metropolitan School District Reorganization Plan" of state defendants February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-2)
      - Michigan State Board of Education
        - Introductory statement February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-3)
        - Neighborhood School Based Metropolitan Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-4)
        - Metropolitan Magnet Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-5)
        - Metropolitan School District Reorganization Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-6)
        - Metropolitan Equal Educational Opportunity and Quality Integration Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-7)
        - Metropolitan One-Way Movement Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-8)
        - Detroit Metropolitan Racial Proportion Criteria Plan February 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-9)
      - State defendants (Milliken, Kelley, MI Department of Education, et al.)
        - Response to the metropolitan school district reorganization plan submitted by the State Board of Education March 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-10)
        - [State Superintendent of Public Instruction's] Progress in preparing recommendations for appropriate interim and final arrangements for the (1) financial, (2) administrative and school governance, and (3) contractual arrangements for the operation of the schools within the desegregation area June 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-11)
        - [State Superintendent of Public Instruction's] Recommendations regarding the financial, administrative, and governmental, and contractual arrangements for operating the public schools in the desegregation area during the period of interim desegregation July 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-12)
        - [State Superintendent of Public Instruction's] Recommendations regarding the financial, administrative, and governmental, and contractual arrangements for operating the public schools in the desegregation area during the period of final desegregation July 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-13)
        - Correspondence accompanying State Superintendent of Public Instruction's reports July 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-14)
      - Desegregation Panel (created by order of the Honorable Stephen J. Roth on June 14, 1972)
        - Notice of initial meeting with State Superintendent of Public Instruction John W. Porter June 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-15)
        - Order modifying order for development of plan of desegregation, to add additional panel members June 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-16)
        - Panel members July 1972 (Box 2)
          (2-17)
        - Reports
          - Recommendations of Desegregation Panel regarding additional transportation equipment needed for the implementation of an interim desegregation plan July 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-18)
          - Recommendations of Desegregation Panel regarding cluster reorganization July 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-19)
          - Effect of the reduction in professional staff July 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-20)
          - The Panel's response to the Court's ruling on desegregation area and order for development of plan of desegregation July 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-21)
          - Appendix A: a pupil assignment plan for the Detroit metropolitan area prepared by the panel appointed by the Honorable Stephen J. Roth, in the case of Bradley v. Milliken, et al. 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-22)
          - Minority report and dissent from the final report of the Desegregation Panel August 1972 (Box 2)
            (2-23)
    - Intervention Documents
      - General court documents and administrative materials
        - Proof of mailing: letter dated 12-20-1971, regarding motion to intervene, December 1971 (Box 3)
          (3-1)
        - Notice to counsel for parties seeking intervention March 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-2)
        - Attorneys of record for intervention March 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-3)
        - Recommendations for conditions to be placed on interventions (from plaintiffs, defendants, and intervenor-defendants) March 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-4)
        - Objections to conditions placed on intervenors (of various intervenor-defendants) March 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-5)
        - Amicus curiae motions March-May 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-6)
        - Notice to all counsel of record and counsel for parties seeking intervention as parties or as amicus curiae June 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-7)
      - Motions to intervene
        - Denise Magdowski, et al. (Concerned Citizens for Better Education) August 1970 (Box 3)
          (3-8)
        - Detroit Federation of Teachers
          - Memorandum in support of application for intervention as party defendant November 1970 (Box 3)
            (3-9)
          - Answer of intervening defendant to petition for rehearing of motion of Professional Personnel of Van Dyke et al. to intervene April 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-10)
        - [Plaintiffs'] Memorandum in opposition to motion of Detroit Federation of Teachers to intervene as party defendant November 1970 (Box 3)
          (3-11)
        - Nancy Bird et al. (National Action Group) December 1971 (Box 3)
          (3-12)